Your Majesty.
臣启陛下
The southwest suffered a severe drought at the beginning of the year
西南年初大旱
which caused crop failures.
作物欠收
The refugees fled all the way east
逃难的灾民一路向东
and people died of starvation along the way.
沿途饿殍遍地
The new Prefect of Xiping Port, Liu Changping,
西平港新任刺史刘昌平
wrote a memorial and asked for support.
上书求援
I remember you said
先前不是说
the harvest reduced by less than 30%
欠收不过三成
and there was enough food in stock
各州府库中
in each prefecture, right?
还有足够的存粮吗
Your Majesty.
回陛下
The original plan was
原本是这样
that each prefecture opens its storehouse for relief.
各州府各自开仓赈济
As long as we got through
只要熬过
this time of short supply
这青黄不接之时
and when the autumn harvest came,
迎来秋稻
the disaster would be solved naturally.
灾情自然可解
But it was also poor
可是这二稻收成又不佳
and the grain seedlings were thin and weak.
禾苗盈尺又不结实
In winter,
到了入冬
the refugees are displaced
灾民遍地
throughout the land.
百姓流离失所
What’s more hateful
更可恨的是
is that the tribes in the southwest
西南诸部
have seen the serious disaster in Xiping Port
看到西平港灾情严重
and they get more eager
更加跃跃欲试
to swoop in
他们想要趁虚而入
and invade Dazheng.
侵犯我大徵
At Your Majesty’s discretion.
请陛下定夺
Present the details
将详情呈上
and I’ll think about it.
朕会详加考量
Your Majesty.
陛下
Now even the garrison in Xiping Port
如今就连西平港
(Crop failure makes people dead) is running short of supplies,
驻军补给也开始短缺
(The tribes there try to invade Dazheng) which has affected our soldiers’ spirit.
严重影响我军势气
Now there are people saying everywhere
现在到处有人在说
that the consecutive droughts
说连续大旱
and crop failures
秋稻欠收
are the punishment from Dragon Tail
这是因为触犯了龙尾神
because he is offended.
这是龙尾神在施展惩罚
That’s absurd!
荒谬
Your Majesty.
陛下
The people in the southwest have been worshiping Dragon Tail
西南百姓信奉龙尾神
for a long time.
由来已久
There are also people saying
更有人传说
that only if the messenger of Dragon Tail
只有天启城的
in Tianqi City
龙尾神使者
goes to Xiping Port and holds a sacrifice ceremony
前往西平港祭祀
can the disaster be relieved.
才能稍缓灾情
Your Majesty.
陛下
I’ve also heard such words.
臣也曾听说如此言论
Now those tribes are primed for action.
眼下外族跃跃欲试
I’ve heard that Consort Chunrong
先前曾听闻淳容妃
once met Dragon Tail in her childhood.
幼时逢仙 得遇龙尾神
From then on, the coast of Yuezhou has been peaceful
从此越州海岸风平浪静
and fertile.
五谷丰登
If Consort Chunrong goes to relieve the people in disaster,
如果淳容妃前去赈灾
I’m sure she will appease the people.
定能安抚民心
Your Majesty.
回禀陛下
Xiping Port is thousands of miles away.
西平港远在千里
If we want
如果真的要
to alleviate disaster,
缓解灾情的话
we should send grain from the neighboring place, Yuezhou.
应从临近的越州调粮
Consort Chunrong is a harem.
淳容妃乃是宫中的女眷
I’m afraid she can’t solve
恐怕难以解决
the plight of the southwest.
西南的困顿
Lord Qinghai.
清海公
It’s for sure that we will transfer grain from Yuezhou,
从越州调粮是一定的
but right now, there’s famine in the southwest.
但眼下西南饥馑
People are in panic.
人心惶惶
Since Consort Chunrong
淳容妃既然是
is the messenger of Dragon Tail,
龙尾神的使者
she is the perfect person to go to Xiping Port
代表朝廷
on behalf of the imperial court
前往西平港赈灾
for disaster relief
安抚民心
and to appease the people.
是最合适不过的
Consort Chunrong
淳容妃
is a harem of His Majesty.
乃是陛下的宫眷
She is not an official.
并不是朝臣
How can she show her face in public
岂有这么轻易抛头露面
and go to the southwest for disaster relief?
前往西南赈灾的道理
With the help of a miracle, things will be done with half the effort.
借助神迹 事半功倍
Why not?
何乐不为
Your Majesty.
陛下
Lord Qinghai is right.
清海公说得对
How can we send a harem for disaster relief?
赈灾一事岂可派遣宫眷
Your Majesty.
陛下
We should let the Ministry of Revenue
还是让户部派人
send people to transfer grain as soon as possible.
尽快调粮才是啊
Your Majesty, I’m willing...
陛下 臣愿意
All right.
罢了
I’ll handle this matter
赈灾之事
prudently.
朕自会审慎处之
If there is nothing else...
若没有其他事
Court adjourned.
退朝
Your Highness, there was
淳容妃 就在刚刚
a person called Xiaoliu
有一位叫小六的
who sent a letter to you.
差人送了封信给您
I just made some fish porridge.
我刚刚做了鱼片粥
Have it while it’s hot.
您趁热喝了吧
Fish porridge?
鱼片粥
Who asked you to make it?
谁让你做的
Lord Qinghai sent people
清海公差人送来了
to bring us a pamphlet
记录您平时
of your eating habits and preferences.
饮食喜好的册子
I’m not hungry.
我不饿
Take it away.
拿下去吧
Yes.
是
Yuran.
玉苒
I need you to find some cypress wood
帮我去找一些柏木
or objects made of cypress wood.
或柏木制的器物来
Your Majesty.
陛下
The southwest is suffering from famine.
这西南饥荒
Those tribes in Leizhou never give up
雷州各部又从未死心
trying to annex the southwest sea.
想吞并西南海域
It must be dealt with.
此事终究要治理一番
The spring harvest was poor
春稻欠收
and the autumn harvest also failed.
秋稻又欠收
The granaries of the prefectures are not bottomless.
州府的粮仓不是没有底
Even if we empty them,
就算掏空了它们
it can only last for a while.
也只能应付一时
I know what to do. You don’t need to worry.
朕自有法子 用不着你
Just have some good rest.
你好生休养便是
Your Majesty.
启禀陛下
Treasurer Wu has arrived by order.
司库监吴主事奉旨前来
Greetings, Your Majesty.
微臣参见陛下
Greetings, Lord Qinghai.
参见清海公
You may rise.
平身
Thank you, Your Majesty.
谢陛下
You wrote a memorial to me three months ago
三月前你曾上书给朕
that the Treasury has no place to store gold
说国库黄金无处安放
and the warehouse needs to be expanded.
请求扩建库房
I guess that’s why you came today.
今日来应该是为此事吧
Your Majesty.
回禀陛下
Zhongzhou is rich in gold mines
中州黄金矿脉丰富
and skillful in smelting gold.
冶炼精粹
Seven or eight in ten of the gold in the world
天下黄金
comes from Zhongzhou.
十之七八出自中州
Copper is circulating mostly in the market,
但市面流通的多是铜
so most of the gold goes into the Treasury.
黄金便大半藏入了国库
In recent years,
这几年
the local governments also paid a lot of coppers into the Treasury.
地方缴入国库的铜钱
There is no place to store them anymore.
国库无处堆放
Your Majesty once ordered to exchange the coppers
陛下曾下令将这些铜钱
for gold with the tribes in the southwest.
向西南诸部兑换成黄金
But now the gold price is soaring.
但如今金价飞涨
Even if the tribes in the southwest
即便西南诸部为此
set up lots of checkpoints,
设立诸多关卡
the gold is still flowing uncontrollably
黄金还是无法控制地
into Tianqi.
流入天启
This summer,
今年夏季
there is no room for gold
国库内
in the Treasury.
连黄金亦已无处堆放
Therefore,
是以
I wrote a memorial again three months ago
臣三个月前再次上奏
to make a request for warehouse expansion.
请求扩建库房
In this case, pass down my order.
既然如此 传朕旨意
For the next ten years,
今后十年
only collect 30% of the taxes from the Dazheng people
凡大徵人赋税只交三成
and the rest will be replaced by corvée.
余下的用徭役代替
In addition,
另外
use half of the money and goods
将国库内的
in the Treasury
一半财货拿出
to build canals,
用于修建各地的运河
dams and granaries everywhere.
水渠 堤坝以及粮仓
Well...
这
Half of it?
一半
Of which, two out of ten
其中十之其二
needs to be sent to the southwest,
要送到西南
mainly to Xiping Port,
以西平港为主
to build canals and granaries along the coastline
修建沿线的运河 粮仓
and to prepare armaments.
筹备军备
Your Majesty.
陛下
That’s a lot of gold.
这么多的黄金啊
You just spent it like that?
陛下就这么花出去了
So petty.
小家子气
Only a miser collects money and never spends it.
有进无出 守财奴尔
Putting the Treasury to use at this point
此时动用国库
will bring the gold price
可以令黄金价格平稳
back to normal,
恢复正常
but not for long,
但过不了多久
the gold price will plummet.
金价肯定会大跌
At that time,
到时候
it will suppress every tribe
会对西南的所有部族
in the southwest.
造成打压
Since the Rebellion of Prince Yi,
自仪王之乱以来
you and I don’t want to launch a war again.
你我皆不想再大动干戈
Now there is famine in the southwest,
如今西南饥荒
and those tribes in Leizhou want to take advantage of the situation.
雷州诸部都想趁火打劫
If this can stop them,
若是此举能让他们消停
our strategy of collecting gold in silence
也不枉费你我这三年来
in the past three years
运筹帷幄
will not be wasted.
默默收敛黄金
Even so,
就算如此
the southwest is still volatile.
西南一带依旧动荡不安
I sincerely want to govern Xiping Port
臣真心想请命去西平港
for Your Majesty
为陛下治理西平港
and fix the sore point for good.
去除这块心病
Jianming.
鉴明
It’s a long trip.
长途奔袭
You can’t take it.
你扛不住的
If this is
若这是臣
the last thing I can do for you,
能为你做的最后一件事
I will do it for the sake of
也是成全了你我之间
the time we’ve spent together for years.
多年的情谊
To stay alive is what you should do for me!
好好活下去才是情谊
Don’t say anything else.
你什么都别说了
I will never let you go.
朕绝对不会放你走
Your Majesty!
陛下
Please go to see Consort Chunrong!
您快去看看淳容妃吧
His Majesty has arrived.
陛下驾到
Greetings, Your Majesty.
臣妾参见陛下
Lord Qinghai.
清海公
Consort Chunrong.
淳容妃
Do you know self-harm is a felony?
你可知宫妃自伤乃重罪
I’m not hurting myself.
臣妾并非自伤
Never mind.
罢了
Jianming.
鉴明
Send Consort Chunrong back to Fengwu Palace.
将淳容妃送回凤梧宫
Yes.
是
I dare not trouble Lord Qinghai.
不敢劳烦清海公
I’ll leave.
臣妾告退
What’s wrong with her?
她怎么回事
Mercy, Your Majesty.
陛下恕罪
Consort Chunrong
淳容妃这些日子
barely ate anything these days.
不思饮食
She’s been preoccupied,
心事重重
and now she lost much blood.
现下又流了这么多血
I guess she is too weak now.
想是太虚弱了
Where is the physician?
医官院的人呢
He is on the way here.
在路上
It will take a while.
大概还要一阵子
Bring me the hemostatic powder now.
赶紧把止血散拿过来
Yes.
是
His Majesty only asked you
陛下只让清海公
to send me back.
送我回来
Now that your job is done,
既然差事已经办完了
please go back.
清海公请回吧
The injury on Your Highness
淳容妃身上有伤
needs to be treated in time,
要及时处理
and then I can
陛下那边
report to His Majesty.
臣才好回话
Give it to me.
给我
Please forgive me
如有冒犯
if I offend you in any way.
请淳容妃见谅
Thank you.
有劳了
Stop looking for
以后不要再找
the way to undo Baixi.
解开柏奚之法了
What does it
我做何事
have anything to do with you?
与清海公有何干系
You only see the surface, but you don’t know the whole story.
你只知表象却不知内情
Let me tell you right now.
我现在就告诉你
The most important thing
关于柏奚
about Baixi is nothing else
最重要的不是其他
but blood.
是血
Only those who have the blood of the Fang Clan running in them
唯有流殇方氏血统的人
can undo Baixi.
才可以解开柏奚
- Lord.
公爷 公爷
Fang Jianming.
方鉴明
Looks like there isn’t much time
看来留给你的时间
left for you.
真的不多了
This medical book has been lost
这明典
(Realgar, croton, musk for poison...) for a long time in Zhunian.
在注辇已遗失已久
Your Majesty only took a few days
陛下短短几日
to find the remains in Lanzhou.
就在澜州找到残本
You are lucky.
运气当真是极好的
There is no luck.
哪儿来什么运气啊
I’ve used everyone I can.
这也是穷尽了
Even so,
纵然如此
I only found half of it.
也才找到区区半册
Your Majesty, don’t worry.
陛下别急
Maybe there is the information you want
也许这半本
in this half.
就有陛下想要的信息
I hope so.
希望如此吧
It’s getting late.
时候不早了
Don’t get too tired.
你仔细着身子
Go to rest first.
先去歇息吧
What about Your Majesty?
那陛下呢
I’ll go to sleep after I finish this.
朕看完这些便睡
Your Majesty!
陛下
Lord Qinghai is dying.
清海公不行了
What?!
什么
Your Majesty...
陛下
Go to rest first.
你先歇着
I’ll rest in Jincheng Palace.
朕回金城宫
What’s wrong with His Majesty?
陛下这是怎么了
It’s unusual for His Majesty to be so flustered.
很少见陛下这么慌张
When did it happen?
多久了
Why are you just telling me now?
为什么现在才说
I heard he has been in a coma
听闻已经昏迷了
for hours.
几个时辰了
Now Physician Li
眼下李御医
is trying his best to save him.
正在极力救治
He said Lord Qinghai is in a bad situation
说清海公的情形很不好
and probably he is not gonna make it through the night.
怕是撑不过今夜
Your Majesty!
陛下
It’s cold.
天气冷
Put on some clothes.
您把衣裳穿上啊
How is he?
如何
Greetings, Your Majesty.
臣参见陛下
Lord Qinghai has strong willpower.
清海公他意志力惊人
It’s not easy for him
能坚持这么多日
to hang in there for so many days.
实属不易
It’s just...
只是
The poison of Dawn Flower in Lord Qinghai
清海公体内的
has penetrated the skin into the marrow.
已从肌理渗入到骨髓
I’m afraid...
只怕
It will happen these days.
只怕就在这一两日了
Your Majesty.
陛下
Take care of yourself.
陛下当心龙体啊
I don’t care.
朕不管
I’ll go against the heaven to change his fate
就算是逆天改命
as long as I can keep him alive!
朕也要留住他
There is really nothing I can do.
臣实在是无能为力啊
There...
一定
There must be a way.
一定有办法的
The Storehouse!
府库
Isn’t there a piece of
府库不是还有一段
Dragon Horn in the Storehouse?
应龙角可以续命吗
Go get it.
快去取来
You can’t do this, Your Majesty.
万 万万不可啊 陛下
That’s for Your Majesty to use
那可是陛下
in case of an emergency...
以备不时之需
Go now!
快去
Your Majesty...
陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
遵旨
Jianming.
鉴明
When Prince Yi rebelled,
当初仪王之乱
you were the one who wouldn’t let me go.
是你不肯放手
Now are you going to leave first?
如今你竟要自己先走吗
How am I
你叫朕
going to live with myself?
如何自处
How am I going to face all of this on my own?
你叫朕如何孤身面对
Master!
师父
He swallowed it.
咽下去了
Your Majesty.
陛下
Jianming!
鉴明
How did this happen?
这是为何
How is he?
如何
Congratulations to Your Majesty.
恭喜陛下
Although he didn’t drink down all the medicine,
虽然一碗药没有喝尽
his pulse has stabilized.
但脉象已渐趋平稳
Then this is...
那这是
Dragon Horn is an elixir to extend one’s life.
应龙角本是续命之奇物
Lord Qinghai should be fine
清海公短时间之内
in a short time.
应该无碍
It’s just that the Dawn Flower poison inside Lord Qinghai
只是清海公体内的
hasn’t been removed.
未生花毒素尚未祛除
I’m afraid
恐怕日后得寻到
we need to find
比应龙角
something rarer than Dragon Horn
更加稀罕的灵药
to save Lord Qinghai.
才能护住清海公啊
Your Highness still has a bad appetite?
淳容妃胃口还是不好
Is the porridge too thick
这粥是熬得稠了
or too dilute?
还是稀了
Are the snacks
几样细点心
not palatable?
也不适口吗
It’s just that I have no appetite.
是我自己没有胃口
By the way,
对了
I need you to go to the library
劳烦你跑一趟藏书阁
and find these books on this
将这上面写的书
for me.
帮我找来
Do you want to see
您是要看历朝以来
the records of noble families in the past dynasties?
记录勋贵世家的典籍
Anything that concerns the Fang Clan
只要是和流觞方氏
in Liushang.
有关的
If there is anything missing on this paper,
这笺纸上若有遗漏
please also find it for me.
也请一并帮我找来
You can leave.
都退下吧
- Yes.
是
No one else knows
昨夜鉴明昏倒的事情
that Jianming passed out last night, right?
没其他人知道吧
Your Majesty, don’t worry.
陛下放心
It was handled in a secret way.
此事极隐秘
Tell those
派去各州府
who went to search for the cure in every prefecture
搜寻灵药 医典的人
not to stop.
让他们不要停
If necessary,
若有必要
send more people.
再加派人手
Yes, Your Majesty.
是 遵旨
I’ll tell them to be more careful
奴婢定让他们加倍小心
and not to leak the news.
不得外泄
(No one died of natural causes) There are 14 counties in Dazheng
大徵十四郡
(Sudden deaths in various strange ways) and nine counties rose in rebellion.
九郡揭起反旗
Of which, three counties share a border with Liushang,
其中与流觞接壤者三
so the latter is almost encircled.
几成围剿之势
Lord Chu Fengyi used coercion.
僭王褚奉仪胁裹
Fang Zhiyi pretended to surrender.
方之翊假降
On July 2nd in the 27th year of Lintai,
麟泰二十七年七月初二
Emperor Xiu had a serious fever
瘴热不下
and passed away.
帝修病殁
I was right.
我没记错
The late emperor died
先帝果然崩于
before the last Lord Qinghai.
老清海公方之翊之前
But the book doesn’t say
只是这书上并未写
whether he undid Baixi or not.
老清海公是否解开了
If they didn’t undo Baixi,
若非解开柏奚
there was no way that the late emperor
先帝不可能
died before the last Lord Qinghai.
会先于老清海公病逝
The 48th Lord Qinghai
第四十八代清海公
also died later than the emperor.
也晚于皇帝过世
Your Highness.
淳容妃
I prepared some refreshments for you.
给您准备了些茶点
You didn’t have much at lunch.
您午膳用得少
Have some tea and pastry.
吃些茶点
Have a rest.
稍微歇息一下吧
Since Dazheng was founded,
自大徵开国起
in addition to Master,
不算师父在内
there are 52 Lords Qinghai in total.
总共有五十二位清海公
Among them,
而这五十二位
plus the last Lord Qinghai, Fang Zhiyi,
加上老清海公方之翊
there are 17 Lords Qinghai
总共有十七位清海公
who died later than the emperors.
过世晚于皇帝
I know
臣知道
that the last Lord Qinghai
上一任老清海公
outlived Emperor Xiu by a few years.
比帝修多活了几年
I also know
臣亦知道
that you take Lord Qinghai as a close friend.
陛下视清海公为挚友
Probably you also thought about setting him free.
应该也想过放他自由
There are occasional precedents
这样的事情
like you said.
确实偶有先例
His Majesty is right.
陛下说得没错
There is a way to undo Baixi.
柏奚当真有解
But in all these books,
只是所有的这些书里
there is no mention of Baixi.
竟然丝毫没有提及
There is no way to know
更无从探知
how to undo Baixi.
解除柏奚的方法
Is it true that only themselves
难道真的除了他们本人
can undo it?
无人能解
Is he getting better?
可有起色
Your Majesty.
回禀陛下
I have inserted needles
臣已经施针
to keep vitals stable, inhibit the poison,
为清海公稳气去毒
and close the important joints.
封闭要害
If nothing goes wrong,
如不出意外
he may be awake three days later.
三日之后或可苏醒
Good.
好
I won’t come to Zhaoming Palace
那这几日
in the next few days
朕便不来昭明宫了
lest some should notice it
以免有些人察知所行
and expose this matter.
暴露了此事
Take good care of Lord Qinghai.
好生照看清海公
I’ll come after you
他若有差池
if anything happens to him.
朕唯你是问
Yes, Your Majesty.
遵旨
Good day, Your Majesty.
恭送陛下
Your Highness.
淳容妃
It’s morning now.
天亮了
It’s easy to catch cold sleeping like this.
这么睡容易着凉了
Yuran.
玉苒
Go and find
再去帮我找一些
more books like these for me.
关于此类记载的书籍
Never mind.
罢了
I’ll find them myself.
还是我自己去吧
Please!
求求你们了
- Is there anyone crying outside? - Let me meet her.
宫外可是有人在哭泣
Maybe it’s a maid who gets punished
兴许是做错事
for doing something wrong.
受罚的宫女吧
I didn’t look closely when I came in.
奴婢进来时并未细看
Let me meet her!
让我见见吧
Don’t worry about it, Your Highness.
淳容妃毋需放在心上
It happens all the time in the palace.
这是宫里常有的事
Let’s check it out.
去看看吧
(Fengwu Palace) Please!
奴婢求您了
Go back.
回去吧
Your Highness!
淳容妃
I’m begging you.
奴婢求求您
Please
求求您救救
save my mother and my sister.
奴婢的母亲和妹妹
Only you can save them now.
现在只有您能救她们了
Get up first.
你先起来
Thank you, Your Highness.
谢淳容妃
What happened?
到底发生什么事情了
Tell me.
你告诉我
I’ll help you if I can.
我能帮的一定会帮你
I’m a servant
奴婢本是
of Jincheng Palace.
金城宫的一名粗苦仆役
My family lives in Xiping Port.
家住在西平港
In recent days,
近几日来
there is famine everywhere in Xiping Port.
西平港一带处处闹饥荒
Yesterday,
昨日
my mother wrote me a letter
奴婢的母亲写信来说
that my father and my brother
奴婢的父亲和哥哥
died of starvation.
都已经饿死了
My sister
奴婢的妹妹
also got separated from my mother.
也和母亲走散了
I don’t know what to do.
奴婢实在没有
I can only ask for your help.
只能求您了
Please save them.
您救救她们吧
I’m begging you.
奴婢求您了
Famine?
饥荒
We need the Ministry of Revenue to allocate food
那要户部拨粮
and the prefectures to open the storehouses for relief.
各州府开仓赈济
I’m in the capital.
我人在都中
How can I help your family?
如何能帮你的家人
People out there are saying
外面都已经传开了
that Your Highness
他们说夫人少时遇仙
met Dragon Tail when you were a child.
曾遇到过龙尾神
You are the messenger of Dragon Tail.
是龙尾神的使者
And the famine
而这次饥荒
is a punishment from Dragon Tail
就是因为西南
because building dykes and reclaiming land
填海造堤
enraged him.
才触怒了龙尾神
That’s why he gave us a drought.
降下大旱
People died of starvation
使得西南地区
everywhere in the southwest.
饿殍遍地
People inside and outside the palace are saying
现在宫里宫外都在传说
that if you can go to Xiping Port
如果您能到西平港去
and pray to Dragon Tail,
向龙尾神祈祷
the victims will be saved.
就一定能够拯救灾民的
Please!
奴婢求您了
Please save my family!
救救我的家人吧
They know it’s nonsense,
明知是无稽之谈
but they keep writing memorials to me!
还上书不止
I think it’s obvious
朕看是摆明了
that someone took the lead
有人牵了头
and united them to force me!
将他们联合起来逼迫朕
I will rip out
有朝一日
these remonstrants’
朕终要将
tongues one day!
这群谏臣的舌头给拔了
Please calm down, Your Majesty.
陛下息怒啊
Fang Haishi
方海市她现在只不过是
is only a harem.
宫中的一介女眷
They unanimously want her to relieve disaster.
众口一词要她去赈灾
- What can she do? - Your Highness.
她能做什么
- Yes. - She was an officer and she is young.
是
If she goes to coordinate the prefectures,
让她来协调各州府
before she gets there and starts to work,
人还没到 灾还没赈呢
she will lose a layer of skin first.
就被扒了一层皮
Your Majesty, Consort Chunrong presents herself.
启禀陛下 淳容妃求见
You senseless thing.
叫你个
Get out!
快出去
Your Majesty.
陛下
I’m here to assist Your Majesty
我正是来协助陛下
to deal with the tricky political affairs.
解决棘手政务的
Greetings, Your Majesty.
臣参见陛下
Rise.
平身
The harem shall not interfere in state affairs.
后宫不得干政
Just leave if there is nothing else
你若无事赶紧退下
lest others should talk about it.
以免惹人非议
I can’t decline to shoulder a responsibility
西平港赈灾
to relieve the people in disaster in Xiping Port.
臣当仁不让
Do you want to go to Xiping Port?
你要去西平港赈灾
Since the officials and the people have presented a petition,
既然朝臣跟百姓
I beg for Your Majesty’s permission.
还请陛下恩准
I’ll go to the southwest
臣前往西南
to coordinate the prefectures
协调各州府
for disaster relief.
赈济灾情
Ridiculous!
胡闹
Do you know
你可知
how dangerous the southwest is?
西南现在是龙潭虎穴
I know.
臣知道
The victims are everywhere in the southwest.
西南如今灾民遍地
If we don’t appease the people,
如若安抚不好
there may be a rebellion.
或许有人揭竿而起
Once there is civil unrest,
一旦引起民乱
I will bear the brunt
臣必首当其冲
and become the target.
成为所有人的靶子
At that time,
到时候
I’ll get killed anyway.
我想不死都不成了
It’s more than that.
不止
Yes.
是不止
Xiping Port has been engaged in
西平港经营
maritime trade for years.
海上贸易多年
Although it’s no better than Nanhuai in Wanzhou,
虽不比宛州的南淮
there are still rich and powerful businessmen everywhere.
但那里世家 豪商遍地
The prefectures were established by the imperial court,
各州府虽都由朝廷设立
and the officials were also dispatched from the capital,
官员也都由都中派遣
but these people had long been
但这些人
associated with the local gentry.
常年与当地的士绅往来
They may not be of one mind.
未必与都中全然一条心
Now the disaster is severe.
如今灾情严重至此
I think most of the prefectures have problems.
各州府大都有问题
Perhaps
或许
even the amount of grain
就连他们每年
stored in their warehouses
上报上来的
that they report every year
仓库中存粮的储量
is wrong.
都有虚实问题
You know how complicated the situation is,
你明知情形复杂
but you volunteer to go.
还敢自荐
Are you so confident?
难不成你有把握
I am not totally confident.
臣没有全然的把握
Only 30%.
只有三成而已
30%?
三成
I think
臣认为
as long as
世上的事
you are 30% confident about something,
只要有三成的把握
you can give it a try.
便可一搏
Besides,
况且
I’m confident that I can rise to the occasion.
臣自信有机变
After I get to Xiping Port
去到西平港
and check the situation myself,
实地考究以后
I’ll be 50% confident.
臣便能有五成把握
And other officials
而朝中其他的官员
would be 50% confident at best.
至多也就五成把握
You may not fully trust them,
他们 陛下未必全信
but you can fully trust me.
而臣 陛下可以全信
No.
不可
I won’t put you at risk.
朕不可让你涉险
Your Majesty, I know you cherish me.
臣知陛下爱护臣
But being a loyal subordinate
但为臣之义
is to devote oneself
不过青山埋忠骨
to the country.
马革裹尸还
As long as I can save the people from suffering
只要能解百姓之苦
and solve the problems of Dazheng,
解大徵之忧
I’m willing to take the risk.
臣愿涉险
This is the value of my existence.
这才是臣存在的价值
Your Majesty,
还请陛下
please don’t make me hide in the capital
不要让臣躲在都中
like a bird in a cage,
犹如笼中之鸟
wearing down my spirit.
日渐消磨斗志
I beg for Your Majesty’s permission
还请陛下恩准
to let me go to Xiping Port.
让臣前往西平港
Mu Deqing.
穆德庆
Yes.
奴婢在
Bring me
将朕的巡天之印
the Seal of Inspection.
取来
Yes, Your Majesty.
遵旨
Have you
近日
been to Zhaoming Palace these days?
可曾去过昭明宫
Your Majesty.
回禀陛下
I don’t like going out.
臣一向不爱走动
I’ve been staying at Fengwu Palace
近日都在凤梧宫
and reading as a pastime.
读书消遣
Your Majesty.
陛下
Receive the imperial edict, Fang Haishi.
方海市领旨
With this Seal of Inspection,
携此巡天之印
you can act on my behalf.
你便是朕的身外之身
Wherever you go,
所到之处
the governors and magistrates
诸州府县主官
will be all at your disposal.
皆任由你调度
I order you to leave for Xiping Port immediately
朕令你速速前往西平港
to relieve people in disaster
赈济灾情
without fail.
不得有误
Yes, Your Majesty.
臣方海市 遵旨
Your Majesty.
陛下
I have a favor to ask you.
臣还有一不情之请
Young Master Haishi.
小公子
Do I still look like
你看我如今
a young master?
还有小公子的样子吗
Consort Chunrong.
淳容妃
Lord is not here.
公爷 他没在
Shaozi.
哨子哥
Today
我即日起
I will leave for Xiping Port for disaster relief
便要前往西平港赈灾
under His Majesty’s order.
有陛下手诏
I need you to send some men to help me.
还请你拨派人手协助我
I’ll dispatch soldiers for you immediately.
臣立刻着手 拨派人手
Thank you.
有劳了
There’s no need to tell that person I came.
不必告诉那个人我来过
I’ll leave.
告辞
Good day, Your Highness.
恭送淳容妃
It’s easy
这西南一带
to go to the southwest,
进去容易
but difficult
出来
to leave.
难
Your Highness is a strategic genius.
还是殿下您运筹帷幄啊
Without a stir,
不动声色地
you put Fang Haishi
就让那方海市
on a road of no return.
走上了不归之路
She used the story of meeting an immortal
她以遇仙为由
to fish for fame and credit.
沽名钓誉
She offended Dragon Tail.
冒犯了龙尾神
It’s a capital crime.
本该就是死罪
Now there are victims everywhere in the southwest.
如今西南是灾民遍地
If her trick is discovered
倘若她被戳穿
and she dies there,
死在了那里
even Fang Jianming who made up the story
就连造谣的方鉴明
will be held accountable for it.
也难有个交代啊
Your Highness.
殿下
You’re killing two birds with one stone.
您这是一箭双雕啊
Speaking of Fang Jianming,
说到方鉴明
I think I haven’t seen him
好像有两三日
for two or three days.
没见到他了
He didn’t show up in the morning session.
早朝也没露脸
Yeah.
是啊
He hasn’t shown up for a few days.
有几日没见着他了
Secretary Shi also said
施主事也说了
that he didn’t see him walking around
这几日啊
in the palace these days.
不见他在宫中走动啊
Did Fang Jianming leave the capital?
方鉴明离开都中了
There are our men at every gate.
各城门都有咱们的眼线
There is no news
没有方鉴明
of Fang Jianming leaving.
离开的消息啊
If he neither
如果说他
secretly left the capital
没有秘密离开都中
nor showed up in public,
又没有露面
maybe he has been
或许是因为伤病
hiding somewhere
猫了起来
because of sickness.
也是有可能的
I’ll send a message to Secretary Shi
我立即传话给施主事
and ask him to find out what happened.
叫他探明真相
If Fang Jianming
倘若这方鉴明
is sick indeed
真的有伤病在身
and can’t show up,
不能露面
then Fang Haishi is out there alone
那方海市独身在外
without his help,
孤立无援
and this show
那这场戏
is going to be more interesting.
岂不是更好看了
Yes.
是
Madam Pearl
斛珠夫人
will go on an inspection tour
替朕巡狩
to the southwest for disaster relief.
前往西南赈灾
The trip is hard.
一路不易
May things go well for Madam Pearl
愿斛珠夫人此去顺遂
and may she return safely soon!
早日归朝
Farewell, Your Majesty.
臣妾拜别
You may rise.
平身
Didn’t you say
你不是说三日之内
he would wake up in three days?
定能醒来吗
This is the fifth day!
这都已经第五日了
Why isn’t he getting any better?
为何一点起色都没有
Mercy, Your Majesty.
请陛下恕罪
I...
臣
I’ve tried my best.
臣已然尽力
I’ve used needles and burned mugwort.
施针 烧艾
I’ve done everything
凡能想到的办法
I can think of.
全都一一用上了
But Lord Qinghai is still in a coma.
但清海公如此昏睡下去
I...
臣
There’s nothing I can do about it.
臣也无计可施啊
You...!
你
Your Majesty!
陛下
Consort Shurong sent a message
淑容妃命人传话
that she found something in the medical book
说是在明典中有所发现
and she asked to see you now.
让您赶快去一趟
I’ll be there right now.
朕这就过去
I’ll hold you accountable if anything happens to him!
若有闪失 朕唯你是问
Wait outside.
你先出去候着
Yes.
是
Bizi, leave us.
碧紫 你也出去吧
You found something in the medical book?
你说明典中有所发现
When Bizi
刚刚碧紫
was pouring tea for me,
在给我倒茶的时候
she accidentally spilled some on it.
不小心在这上面
What does that mean?
这是什么意思
This is the ancient language of Zhunian.
这是注辇古语
It says
上面说的是
no matter
凡中毒者
what the poison is,
不论何毒
the one who is poisoned can be cured
若有龙尾神眷顾
with Dragon Tail’s blessing.
皆可痊愈
Dragon Tail’s blessing?
龙尾神的眷顾
Except for Fang Haishi,
除了方海市之外
I’ve never heard of
朕还从未听说过
anyone else who met Dragon Tail.
有谁真的见到过龙尾神
Was there anyone who got poisoned
那从前中毒的人
going to sea in search of Dragon Tail?
可曾出海寻找过龙尾神
Yes.
是有人去过
But I’ve never heard of
但是从未听说
anyone returning with a cure.
有人带解药回来
When I was a child,
臣妾小时候
I heard some stories
在注辇的王宫
in the palace of Zhunian
听到过一些故事
that some people went to sea
有些人出海
to ask Dragon Tail for the cure,
去寻找龙尾神赐药
but Dragon Tail didn’t grant.
但龙尾神并未赐予
At that time, people thought
那时候大家都以为
it was the elixir of life.
那是长生不老之药
But now it seems
但现在看来
that it could be the antidote.
有可能是解毒之药
Is there anything else on it
那这上面是否还有
that says something specific
有没有提到
about the cure?
解毒的具体方法
No.
没有
In this case,
这么说的话
I think it’s probably just a legend
朕觉得
and a wish.
和寄愿了
Your Majesty.
陛下
Well,
是这样的
it mentioned in a Leizhou legend
在雷州数千年
passed down orally
口口相传的传说里
for generations
曾提及
that the hair, blood
龙尾神的发丝
and scales of Dragon Tail
血和鳞片
can be used as medicine to save lives.
均可以入药救人
Since there are such records
既然明典上
in the medical book,
有这样的记载
it means these legends
那就说明这些传说
may not be meaningless.
不一定是没有意义的
In that case, what about luminous pearls?
如此说来的话 鲛珠呢
Can that work?
鲛珠是不是也可以
Luminous pearls...
鲛珠
Luminous pearls are the tears of Dragon Tail.
鲛珠是龙尾神的眼泪
It should be able to work.
应该可以
Luminous pearls, right.
鲛珠 对啊
Thank you, Tilan.
谢谢你 缇兰
Your Majesty, don’t say that.
陛下不要谢我
You said
陛下不是说过嘛
that husband and wife should share the burden together.
夫妻就是要一起分担的
About Dawn Flower...
关于未生花
I...
朕
You don’t need to explain.
陛下不必解释
I don’t know the details,
缇兰虽不知详情
but I know
但知道
you are worried about something.
陛下是在担忧些什么
Your Majesty, go and save that person now.
陛下快去救人吧
Mu Deqing, hurry.
穆德庆 快
Your Majesty.
陛下
Go and get luminous pearls
去把斛珠夫人
from Madam Pearl’s dowry.
陪嫁的鲛珠拿来
Yes.
是
Your Majesty.
陛下
The pearls have been ground up for use as medicine.
医官院已将鲛珠
Come on.
过来
Jianming.
鉴明
Fang Haishi has left for the southwest.
方海市已经去了西南
If you leave now,
你若就此撒手
you will be separated from her forever,
就真的是天人永隔了
and she will regret it for the rest of her life.
她定会抱憾终身
At that time,
到时候
I don’t know if I can keep her safe.
朕都不一定能保得住她
Therefore,
因此
even for her sake,
就算是为了顾念她
you must wake up soon.
你也要赶紧醒过来
Do you understand?
明白吗
Jianming! Jianming!
鉴明 鉴明
Jianming!
鉴明
Physician! Physician!
御医
This is...
这
What’s wrong with him again?
这又是怎么了
How is he? How is he?!
如何 如何
Your Majesty, don’t worry.
陛下毋需担心
I think the luminous pearls
应是鲛珠将体内的毒素
forced some poison out of his body.
逼出来了一些
Lord Qinghai
清海公
is safe for now.
暂时没有性命之忧了
Can these pearls
这些鲛珠
clean
能否将他
all the poison in his body?
体内的余毒清除
I don’t know yet.
这个尚未可知
It’ll take a few more days
需得再仔细观察
to tell.
才能断定
Your Highness.
淳容妃
We will arrive in Xiping Port
还有一个时辰
two hours later.
便可以到达西平港了
Wake up.
醒醒
Get up. Get up.
起来 起来
Mother.
娘
Just as they said,
果然如他们所说
people are suffering from starvation in the southwest
西南饥馑
and there are victims everywhere.
到处都是灾民
How is the situation inside the city?
城中情况如何
Strangely,
说来奇怪
there are so many victims,
灾民如此之多
but they’re all from the surrounding prefectures.
却都是周边府县的人
There aren’t
西平港
fewer people inside the city.
城内并没有多少减员
Instead, people are gathering there.
反而有人聚集
I found it quite strange.
奴婢觉得事有蹊跷
People are gathering there?
有人聚集
Is it because they opened the storehouse for disaster relief?
或许是因为开仓赈济吗
But a few months ago,
可是几个月前
the Prefect of Xiping Port, Liu Changping,
西平港的刺史刘昌平
wrote a memorial
已上书
that the storehouse was running out of food
说西平港仓中粮食告急
and there was no food left.
已无余粮了
I’ve been to Xiping Port before.
我之前来过西平港
At that time, Mr. Chen Heran
当时还是陈赫然陈大人
was the Prefect of Xiping Port.
是西平港的刺史
Xiping Port was thriving.
整个西平港风气蔚然
I don’t know much about
如今调来这位刘大人
Mr. Liu who has just been transferred here.
倒不知是何许人也
Keep an eye on him for me.
你且帮我多留意他
Yes, Your Highness.
奴婢遵旨